So this is lecture 10. We're going to take a brief respit from scaling
laws. Um and we're going to talk about inference. So the question of inference
is a very simple one. Given a fixed model that we've trained, generate responses
given prompts. Okay. Um first we're going to start by understanding what the implications
of inference are um and the workload um that it entails. Um and then
we're going to talk about ways of making inference uh faster. And throughout this
lecture you're going to see that there's a lot of inference is a very
deep topic. It's actually the uh we didn't do inference uh last year in
lectures. So this is the first year we're doing it. But there's actually many
many topics that could span multiple lectures which I'll try to condense into one.
So inference shows up in multiple different places. The most obvious place is if
you actually want to use a model, you want to use it to chat.
Um you're using cursor or something to do code completion. If you're running batch
a data processing job using your language model, all of these cases demand inference
because you need to generate tokens from your actual model. But it also shows
up in other contexts. If you want to even evaluate your model um let's
say on instruction following you need to do inference. Um there's a lot of
interest in test time compute which means uh thinking more before um you actually
output some um uh the final answer and that's also more inference because thinking
is basically generate tokens. And then finally, even training itself, if you're using reinforcement
learning, you need to sample responses and then evaluate them based on some reward.
And that also requires inference. So inference isn't just I want to put up
a chatbot demo. Inference actually is going to underly many of the basic functions
of a language model. And even though it's one lecture, I want to stress
how actually important it is for uh many things. And we'll probably come back
to this when we talk about um in alignment um later in the class.
So now inference is important. So the theme of this class is efficiency and
efficiency clearly matters. Training is a one-time cost but inference you repeat multiple times.
So here's some you know anecdotal uh um stats on why inference is a
big deal. So Sam says OpenAI generates a 100red billion words a day which
is quite a quite a lot. Um and even cursor which is not that
new of a a product is um allegedly generating a billion lines of accepted
code um each day. So um it's just giving you an idea of how
much inference is accounting for and you know costs of inference compared to training
um are definitely you know increasing. So how do you measure what inference good
inference looks like? So there's time to first token TTFT. So this is how
long a user an individual user needs to wait before any generation happens at
all. And this matters clearly for interactive applications. If you have a big prompt
and then you have to wait there for 10 seconds, that may not be
a good user experience. Latency is how fast tokens are arriving after maybe the
first first token. Um this also matters for interactive um applications. Throughput is is
something a bit different. Throughput is um how many tokens in general are generated
per not for overall users. So this is it's particularly useful in batch processing
applications. So you can think about the throughput is um high throughput doesn't mean
low latency because uh some you know requests might just take a very long
time and you still have high throughput. Latency is is kind of like the
you know worst case over any individual
user. So what do you need to uh think about when you think about
the efficiency of inference? Um so in training um the the key idea is
that you get to see all the tokens at least a supervised training which
means that you can parallelize over the the sequence. This is exploited heavily in
the transformer, right? So you've done the transformer training. You know that you basically
construct these tensors over the entire sequence and it's just like tensor tensor tensor
uh you know mats and then you get your output. But the the key
defining feature of inference at least for transformers is that you have to generate
sequentially. You can't parallelize because um the generation of a a token depends on
all the past. So this is going to be the key thing that's going
to make inference a lot harder and in particular it's going to be harder
to utilize all the compute that's uh available and it's going to be memory
limited as we'll see uh in detail later. So a lot of people are
doing inference. Um anyone who's actually has a product and platform quickly realizes that
these uh cost in doing large models is going to go up. So they
spent a lot of uh time and you know engineering effort trying to reduce
that time. So both providers serving closed models and providers serve open m open
weight models uh pay a lot of attention to um to imprints um more
so than I think the average academic because we're not actually serving any models.
We're just training and getting a score and putting in the paper. But people
who are actually serving models pay a lot of attention to inference. Um so
there's also a bunch of open source packages which are um interesting to to
look at uh as well. Okay. So um I want to understand the inference
workload uh kind of in detail. So I'm going to review briefly um the
sort of this transformer math that we uh um you did in assignment one
and we talked a little bit about it during the the first week of
of class. So this is from the scaling um JXML book which um is
is something you guys should really take a look at. I think it does
an excellent job of outlining many of the of the key concepts um here.
Um and they have this really nice diagram that shows essentially the the computation
graph taking an input and having it go through attention and the MLP layers.
Um in particular um we're going to use this notation. So just to kind
of review this this quickly. So B is the number of sequences in your
batch. L is the number of layers. T is the sequence length. Uh you
can think about as the number of tokens you're going to generate u or
or query using. S is also the sequence length but how many you're um
kind of conditioning on in your prompt. V is the vocabulary. D is the
dimensionality of model. F is the MLP hidden dimension which is usually four times
D. um h is the attention head dimension. N is the number of query
heads. So generally N times H equals D. Um and then in GQA group
query attention you have a different number of key value heads as query heads.
Usually K is smaller than N and um G is the number of um
of groups. Um so K * G equals N. Okay. Okay. And this diagram
shows that you take your X, you feed through the the Q KV matrices,
um, and you do a bunch of bunch of things.
Um,
okay. So, so remember that the flops required for a fever pass is six
times the number of of tokens, which is B * T times the number
of parameters uh, plus for the tension. there's another order t. So t *
t is t ^2 um dependence. Okay, so let's also review arithmetic and intensity
which is going to help us characterize when something is compute limited versus memory
limited. Um so just to start with the basic you know u map mall.
So let's take a matrix X which is B by B by D and
a matrix W D by F and you know just to give some color
to this uh computation B is the batch size D is the hidden dimension
and F is the up projection matrix in the gated MLP. Um so next
let's do count the number of flops and memory um read and writes u
for just doing X times W. Okay, so we're going to start with um
initialize to zero. And what one has to do for this is we're going
to um read X from HBM. So you that means it incurs a memory
cost of 2 * B * D assuming everything is in BF 16. Um
you also read W. So that's 2 * D * F. Um then you
do the the mat mole and that encurs 2 * um b * d
* f flops. So remember this is from the first lecture so hopefully this
is review. Um and then you have to write it back out which is
you uh have to pay another transfer. Okay. So the total number of flops
is uh just the the mammal and the number of bytes transferred is essentially
the size of all the the matrices that are read and written and arithmetic
intensity is basically the ratio. Um so the ratio is this expression. Um and
in general just to simplify things a bit um generally the batch size is
much less than D and F. um B maybe you know hundreds and a
DNF might be you know thousands or tens of
thousands. Um so I'm using simp here just to keep myself from making silly
mistakes. Um so basically I'm letting C go to infinity um and D scales
as C * B and F scales as C * B and that gets
you a simplified equation of B. Okay. So the arithmetic intensity is B for
this particular matrix multiplication. Um and um and the okay so the way to
interpret this is how many flops are done per bite that was transferred. So
now um the second part is you look at the accelerator which for H100
flops per second
is
um 98989 teraflops memory bandwidth 3.3 ter bytes per second and you divide and
that gives you what is called the accelerator intensity and um if you look
at the computational intensity um which is B if it's greater accelerated intensity that
means you're compute limited that means you're able to use all the the GPUs
or TPUs and if you're less than that then you're memory limited which is
uh you know bad and so you're computer limited in this matrix multiplication case
if B is greater than uh 295 uh for a H100 and all of
this is a bit idealized the actual details there's it's this is giving you
a kind of a first order approximation
um so in extreme extreme case. So generally if you that means if you
use batches of size let's say 300 then you'll be be able to saturate
the GPU. But what happens if your batch is really small? So in particular
B equals 1 which essentially corresponds to a matrix vector product then the arithmetic
intensity is basically one and that is really really bad. that means you're going
to be um memory limited and which which kind of makes sense because basically
you're reading and writing this D times or actually you're just reading this D*
F matrix and you're performing essentially in the same number of flops right so
the ratio between the flops and the reads is the same which is gives
you one and one is bad you want a lot of flops to be
done for any memory read because memory reads are
uh slow But this is in in essence what happens with generation right because
you're proceeding token by token. We'll see that basically um your arithmetic intensity is
going to be like one and that's why uh generation is going to be
memory limited um and not compute limited. Okay. So this is a very simple
example that I think gets at the core of why uh generation is going
to be slow. So maybe I'll pause and take any questions on this um
just to make sure everyone's
clear. Yeah, I mean when doing why don't we have a batch size of
say larger than one. So I think I heard the question why don't we
have a batch size more than one. So I'll get to why you can
uh but there's um batch size is going to mean batch size time sequence
length um
later. Okay. So in summary um matrix multiplications are the kind of the core
computation. So we just studied a matrix multiplication and counted the number of flops
it requires over the number of read and writes and we show that that
ratio which is arithmetic intensity depends on one of the dimensions in case in
this case the batch dimension and that's why big matrices are are good because
that can saturate your um your compute whereas if you have even a thin
matrix um B equals one that's really bad because you're spending a lot of
time reading from memory and not doing that much uh compute. Okay. So um
now let's talk about the arithmetic intensity of of inference. Um okay so let's
let's just uh kind of get more into the weeds of what inference looks
like. So, so the naive thing you can imagine doing and all these nice
pictures are taken from this this book um is that you have a transformer,
you give the prompt in, you gives you logits over the the vocabulary of
the next token and you just sample from that and then once you get
that you attach it to the prompt and then you feed it through the
transformer and you look at the logic sample again and you repeat, right? So
that's um the sort of most naive thing to do. Um and you know
the complexity here is is pretty bad because each token you generate is like
n squ or t squ um you know computation through the through the transformer.
Okay. So that that's no good. But if you look at this closely, you'll
notice that you're doing a lot of redundant work, right? All these um the
work um in basically encoding the prefix basically stays the same. So this is
for a uh for a birectional uh transformer it would be different but at
least for a auto reggressive causal transformer it is the case that you should
be able to share a lot between prefixes and so the solution is you
cache and you cache in the IBM HPM because that's uh where you have
enough space to store stuff. So this is what it looks like if you
have a KV cache in schematically. Um so you take your prompt the prefill
step is you feed it through the transformer and you compute this KV cache
um and then you generate the logits over the next token and then you
um put that into um you know take that generated token and the the
cache and then you can feed it through the transformer. But you've already computed
these so you don't have to do that again. you just need to compute
this new um KV uh vector for this token and now that allows you
to more quickly generate the next um token and and so on. So basically
you're filling up this KV cache which corresponds to the tokens that you've either
prefilled with or generated so far. Okay. So instead of T squ per token,
it's going to be more like T. Okay. So concretely the KV cache is
for every sequence in your batch for every token in your sequence for every
layer of the transformer for every head you're going to store a hdimensional uh
vector. So you might think that this is going to take a lot of
memory and you wouldn't be wrong. Okay. So there's two stages of inference. So
prefill is you're given your prompt encoded a vector. So this is just like
what you do in training. It's paralyzable. It's fast. Your compute limited life is
good. And then you're doing generation which is you're generating response tokens one by
one sequentially. And this is a part that's going to give us a lot
of trouble in terms of uh efficiency. So now let's compute the flops and
memory IO for both the for the transformer. So we're going to break it
down into MLP layers and the attention layers. Um and um just notationwise, we're
going to do this computation with s being the number of tokens we're conditioning
on. Think about the length of the prompt. And T is the number of
tokens we're generating or or quering using. Um and in prefill t is going
to be s because we're sort of I mean we're not generating uh t
tokens, but we're sort of like querying um using each of these tokens. and
a generation where t is
just one. Okay, so hopefully the matrix multiplication is still fresh in your head
because this is going to be essentially that but a little bit more complicated
because it's a transformer. So we're going to count the flops and bytes generated.
Um so first we're going to um take x which is a um b
by t by d u matrix. I think maybe these T's should be S's.
Um but um anyway, so um so that involves doing a bunch of uh
transfers. Um uh basically the size of that matrix times two because BF 16.
Um then there's the the three-way matrices, the up projection, the gate, and the
down They're all the same um you know size up to transposition. Um so
you need to transfer those. Um then you do the um you know up
projection um that's some number of flops. So B * D * C* F.
So whenever you multiply you know two tensors basically the contracting dimension only gets
counted once whereas other dimensions you just you kind of gather together. Um you
need to write it out. You also have the gate which is the uh
same same thing. You write it out. You compute uh your um nonlinearity. You
multiply some stuff and you down project um and that's b * t *
d * f which is basically the same number of flops and you write
um out uh the the result. Okay. Okay. So if you look at the
the counting um I guess maybe I'll just uh you know you can check
the um you know results. Actually you don't need to check it because this
is simp and it's guaranteed to be you know correct. Um so but again
we're going to assume that B * D is much smaller than DN and
F and we get that the intensity is B * T. Okay. So this
is analogous to the matrix uh multiplication case where the in arithmetic intensity which
we want to be high depends on how large your batches and how many
tokens you're you're essentially generating. Okay. Okay. So now if you look at the
two stages prefill life is good remember because we can just make BT large
enough you use a batch size even a batch size of one actually is
is maybe okay if you have long enough uh sequence um so that's not
a problem. Now generation this is where it becomes a little bit harder because
you're generating one token at a time. So T is one right? So if
t is one that means for bt to be large you need b to
be large and b is essentially the number of concurrent requests. Okay. So this
is kind of interesting because your your sort of efficiency depends on um having
large batch sizes because I mean intuitively it makes sense if you can take
a lot of requests batch them together then uh you can get um you
know better uh efficiency at least throughput. Um, but this also depends on what
um B is because if it's um you're only getting a few requests at
a time, then you're not going to be able to use your hardware very
efficiently. Um, and this is talks speaks to the sort of the very dynamic
aspect of inference which we'll come back to later in the lecture. Okay, so
now what about attention? Turns out attention is even worse um for reasons I'll
I'll try to get into. So let's do the counting flops um bytes transferred.
Okay. So I'm going to read the QKV um matrices
from HPM. I'm going to compute the the tension which is a matrix which
is Q * K. And the number of flops is B * S *
T * D. So remember S and T are the same during a prefill.
So that's your um sequence length squared times b * d and then um
I'm I'm sort of only looking at the matrix multiplications because the flops from
the other steps don't really matter. Um and then you project out to your
uh oh sorry you you take a combination of this and v. So actually
this is mathematically incorrect because there's some soft maxes there but the essence of
the map malls are are the are the same. So that's the same number
of flops and then you write to HPM. Okay. So and here I'm assuming
there'll be more bytes transferred if you didn't use fly flash attention. Flash attention
means that you don't have to keep on writing back to HPM intermediate steps.
So um but the order is actually not u really affected. So qualitatively doesn't
really uh matter whether you use flash attention or not but the the math
here depends on the con the constants matter. Um but let's look at the
flops and the bytes transferred and if you uh divide and simplify you get
this rather nice expression. I mean nice in that it's simple, not nice in
that it's uh it's good efficiency which is S * T / S plus
T. Okay, so let's try to interpret this a bit. So in prefill T
equals S. So that means your prefill intensity is order S. So that's good,
right? Because as long as you have long enough uh you know sequences then
uh you're you're you know good to go right and generally the sequences can
you assume are kind of long enough. Um during generation however um you'll see
that the entity is uh essentially one s over s+ one but that's basically
one um and remember one is is really bound. Okay. So, but but notice
like what there's no dependence on V at all. So, unlike in MLPS, remember
in MLPS um the the generation the prefill was BT which is great um
and then arithmetic intensity was B which was not great because it depends on
the whims of your users and workloads but still could be larger than one.
Whereas um for attention it's actually just always less than one. No matter how
many how long your sequences there are, how how how many users there are
um it's always one. So why why is this intuitively that there's no dependence
on on B the batch dimension. So the reason is that in the MLP
layers intuitively every sequence hits the same MLP weights. So whereas in attention layer
each sequence has its own uh KV cache right because the KV cache is
sequence specific which means that you you can't really you know uh use in
ML case you can kind of read all the weights and then you process
a batch intuitively whereas in attention case um every sequence kind of requires additional
memory you don't get any kind of savings if you um if you kind
of batch them up mathematically I guess you can look at it through here
where um the number of flops there's a b here which is expected but
the number of bytes transferred is um you know b times um there's a
scaling in in b so when you divide that b uh cancels um whereas
over here um there is a b here but um we're assuming the df
f dominates. So when you divide um basically there's no b essentially left in
the the denominator. So you can look at it mathematically or you can just
kind of reason about it intuitively as um during for the attention the kv
cache is sort of every sequence's own unique uh
snowflake. Okay. So the summary is prefill is compute limited whereas generation is memory
limited. Um the MLP arithmetic intensity is B. Um which to make good enough
you need bunch of concurrent requests but attention intensity is one which and it's
also impossible
to
improve that. Okay. I'll pause bit for any any questions. Okay. So let's let's
move on. Um so now we know that inference it due thanks to generation
is memory limited. Let's uh try to study the throughput and latency um um
at least in in theory um so let's focus on let's see actually okay
so um we're going to make some assumptions. So all of this is sort
of napkin math is a little bit stylized um but it gives you roughly
the right kind of scaling and the right way to think about things. So
we're going to assume that commu communication and compute can be perfectly um overlapped
which is obviously false but it's it's good enough for for making these qualitative
uh um estimates. Um so what we're going to do is we're going to
instantiate the latency and throughput for a llama 2 13B on H100. Okay. So
for a
13B um here are the values. So the se let's just put the sequence
length to be a th00and hidden dimension to be model dimension to be 5,000
four times uh I don't know if that's that's not four times but anyway
f is um some multiple of that number of heads number of uh key
value um I guess uh query heads number of key value heads which for
llama 2 is the same we'll get to that point later um and and
so on and for the memory bandwidth of H100 that's the Okay, so that's
uh the config and we're going to compute the the memory latency and throughput.
Okay, so Oh, okay. Um so first uh let's just quickly get the number
of parameters. You guys did this in assignment one. So I won't bel labor
this but it's some expression. Um that depends on all the different knowh um
and uh the to store the parameters we're going to use f B bf16
um because inference is generally going to be 16 bit not 32-bit um so
we're going to multiply between two. So that's the memory that the parameters take.
Okay, we don't need gradients. We don't need optimizer states because we're not training.
But we do have to store the KV cache which are the act some
of the activations um not all the activations but some of them for every
sequence of length s and how much we have to per store per sequence.
It's basically the sequence lengths times the number of key value uh um heads
times the dimension of that head times the number of layers times um basically
two for basically both a key and a value and two for BF 16.
Okay, so that's how much the cache size uh takes. Um and so the
total memory is batch size times the cache per sequence plus the memories uh
plus the parameter size. So now latency is going to be determined by memory.
Remember it's memory limited. So we're just going to compute how much memory needs
to be transferred uh into the GPU to do this computation. is simply memory
over the memory bandwidth. Um, and throughput is essentially the inverse of latency but
scaled up by B because we're looking at generating B tokens in in parallel.
Okay. So now if we substitute our um llama 2 config um we'll see
that the number of parameters checks out it's it's um you know 13 billion
roughly the memory latency and throughput have these expressions um so memory you know
grows obviously this is the parameter size this is the key value uh cache
size times times B latency also goes up as a function of B throughput
um um increases but you'll see that it increases up to a point. The
B shows up in both the numerator and the denominator. Um so there's limits
to how much you can stretch throughput even if you could fit everything in
memory. Okay. So those are um the expressions uh for latency throughput and memory
for this particular model. So now let's instantiate with different batch sizes. So if
B equals 1 um then the latency is about 8 milliseconds. So 8 mill
every 8 you generate a token and the throughput is 124 uh tokens uh
per second. Okay. So that's 13B on a H100 um if you're using batch
size of one. So now what happens if you use um batch size
of
16? So you'll see that the um the memory usage increases because you need
to store the KV cache for all 64 sequences. Now the latency goes up.
Um because you kind of have to instead of just processing one, you have
to kind of wait for everything to finish. Um but the throughput also goes
up actually quite a lot. Okay. So you're seeing kind of this uh immediate
trade-off between latency and throughput. If you want low latency, you just use one
um one uh B equals 1. But if you want high throughput, you want
larger B in general. Um what happens if you use a batch size of
even larger?
So 256. Um you'll see that the latency goes up, throughput goes up, but
you see that throughput isn't going up that much because you get diminishing returns
after a while. But the most kind of uh you can't actually do this
on a 100 because if you look at the uh the memory it's 240
uh gigs. So it doesn't even fit. Okay. So batch size you can only
increase to a certain point um because of memory. Okay. So just to recap,
there's a trade-off between latency and throughput. Smaller batch sizes yield battery latency. larger
batch sizes yield better uh throughput. And finally, there's uh we talked last week
talked about parallelism for training and it was, you know, kind of complicated, annoying.
Um at least one type of parallelism for inferences is really really nice and
simple. Um you just launch M copies of the model. Okay, no communication because
the model you don't need to update the models. the latency is the same
and the throughput increases by m. So that's that's pretty good. So always remember
that uh you know don't forget easy things. Um now there are cases where
you if you have a large enough model then uh maybe it doesn't even
fit on a single uh GPU and you need to shard the model and
in this case you also want to uh start sharding the KV cache in
some cases um to get you know better you know efficiency. So um there's
for more details uh check out this uh book chapter. Okay. So uh the
time to first token um which is a metric I mentioned earlier is essentially
a function of of the prefill. It's basically how long does it take to
encode the prompt and usually it's uh you know this is compute limited so
you're basically going as fast as you can. Um and there's not much you
can do about it given a fixed architecture.
Um and uh well okay so sorry you you can improve it if you
um if you reduce the the batch size uh still um but if you
want to improve the throughput you have to um you know increase the batch
size. Okay so any uh questions about that? So this was on computing the
throughput and latency and because of the memory limited uh argument that I gave
in the the previous um part I just focus on memory and compute how
many bytes need to be sent and that gives me uh a rough bound
on um the latency. In practice the compute there are some regimes where compute
does matter but I'm sort of ignoring that just u to keep things
simple. Okay, a question. Is this assuming a single GPU? Uh the qu Yes,
this is assuming a single GPU. Uh while creating a batch from multiple users,
uh each of these will be completed
different tokens.
Yeah. So the question is if you have multiple users and you're batching them
together, they might arrive at different times. They're going to finish at different times.
So, we're going to get to that. Um, that's going to be a special
issue that we're going to have to
deal with. Any other
questions? Okay, so now we have a good handle on what the inference workload
looks like. U, we looked at the arithmetic intensity. We looked at the the
transformer inference with respect to in arithmetic intensity. We saw that it was memory
limited thanks to the tension where the KV cache has to be special for
every sequence and then using that we can compute throughput and and latency which
are the main inference metrics that we we care about. Now how do we
make things better? Okay, so there are some things that you can do on
that lossless. You can write better kernels. You can improve your your systems. But
I would say that the the high kind of there's a lot you can
do if you're willing to take uh you know shortcuts. Um and these are
kind of really interesting because technically this lecture is on inference but secretly it's
on model architectures because what you'll see is that a lot of the changes
in model architecture are going to have direct impact on inference and we're actually
inspired by needing to do inference quickly. Okay, so the big bottleneck here is
the KV cache, right? Because remember memory limited, which means that the less memory
stuff takes um then the faster you go. Not just because of flops, even
though that's the part of it, but mostly due to memory because um it's
mostly about the memory transfers. If that's one thing you take away from this
lecture, it's like all about the the kind of the memory uh for speed.
Okay. So the the problem is that if you just start whacking away at
the KV cache, you're you might lose accuracy. So how can you make sure
you don't lose too much accuracy but still uh maintain um your your KV
cache uh small? So there's a bunch of ideas I'm going to go through
um that all essentially try to change the architecture to reduce your KV cache.
Some of these ideas I think you you've seen um but I'll go through
them kind of in this sort of more systematic way. So there's this idea
called group query attention. So multi-headed attention which is the vanilla transformer keeps around
uh basically number of heads and for each of the that number you have
same number keys values and queries. Um there was one time a multi-query attention
which you only have one uh key and one value basically one key value
head. Uh turned out that that was not very expressive. So there is a
sort of intermediate point where um you have a reduced number of keys and
values and then you have more queries. So why are we doing this? Well
remember we want to reduce the KV cache size. So the fewer keys and
values there are the better. So the batch size and the sequence length doesn't
uh get changed but it's and the dimensionality of the the these vectors don't
change but it's the number of key value heads that
we're
reducing. Okay. So, so that's basically the idea and this paper shows that you
do get latency and throughput um improvements. So, times per sle sample and as
you increase the number of groups um then uh up to eight or so
basically there's a negligible um uh is it's really fast compared to um the
full attention. Um and as you increase the number of groups obviously you kind
of end up at the the original. So that's uh latency and throughput
improvements. Um and just to actually do this kind of more rigorously. So we
have our llama 213 uh B model. And if we compute the the
statistics um this is using a batch size of 64. Remember this is what
we got. Um uh I guess I should have printed out latency here. Oh
well. Um and then um if you run it with GQA you see that
the memory is reduced and the throughput goes way up. So this is actually
great. Um so this is what happens if I take the llama to 13b
architecture and I just reduce for every query head I'm going so for every
key value head I have five query heads that's what 1:5 ratio means um
so which this also means we can use a larger batch size because remember
last time we tried to do 256 it didn't even fit in um an
H100's memory so now um we can actually comfortably fit into the H100 memory
and then we can further improve the throughput by using a larger batch size.
So you can see kind of a lot of different effects here. By reducing
the number of uh key value pairs, the memory of the KV cache reduces.
Um that means the the throughput and latency go up automatically because fewer memory
transfers and furthermore as a secondary effect I can increase the batch size within
the GPU and that further improves the throughput.
Okay. So that's that's wonderful. Um we have to also make sure the accuracies
doesn't drop. So this is um this original paper that shows that uh this
is full attention. This is GQA. Um the time is much less but the
accuracy is basically
the same. Okay. Now um you know what actually happened? So I don't uh
so llama 2 did not use this ratio but llama 3 actually picked up
you know GQA and um you know probably motivated by the kind of inference
costs actually llama 2 I think the 70 the large model did have GQA
but not the smaller ones okay so that's GQA there's another way to reduce
the key value cache and this comes from deepseek So this is actually from
the v2 paper and it's called multi head latent which tatsu lectured about uh
previously but I'll try to um talk about it in the context of inference
and its implications. So the basic idea is uh here's full attention and GQA
says I'm going to use fewer keys and values. MLA says I'm not going
to change the number of key and values. I'm going to project these into
a lower dimensional space. So, it's another way of shrinking the KV size, but
just in a I guess in a different
um dimension. So, instead of using N* H dimensions for each uh um for
the KV cache of each uh you know uh token, I'm going to project
out to C dimensions. Um and this is what Deep Seek did. It's actually
quite a aggressive reduction from 16,000 to 512. Only wrinkle is that this is
not compatible with rope. So they need to add a few more more dimensions
to put rope back in. But overall, this is actually quite uh promising um
from a KV reduction perspective. I'm not going to do the math. you can
but you can just trust me that you can see kind of how the
KV cache would be reduced a lot and you get the same kind of
latency and throughput advantages. Um, and in terms of accuracy, they actually showed um
that compared to GQA um the MH uh sorry, the um actually maybe I'm
showing the wrong thing
here. Um maybe okay. Um I meant to show that the um MLA actually
improves, but this table does not show that. So I'll have to um dig
that up later. But but anyway it MLA does um preserve the the accuracy
as well. Okay. So there's another idea which says well um you know GQA
basically shares you can think about it as a sharing key value uh vectors
right within um a token and within a um sequence. Um but we can
also look at something called cross layer attention which uh there's a paper on
this but I think many people have been kind of uh thinking about this
and doing this uh so I don't know know if this is actually the
first paper but basically if you look at the transformer I diagram um you
have the key value projection of one layer and then you have the next
layer and these key value um vectors are separate um usually um but IDE
idea here with uh CLA is that we're just going to use the same
key value projection across layers. That's why it's called cross layer
attention. Um
so just as GQA shares across heads, CLA shares across layers. So here we
they show that they empirically improve the paralo frontier of accuracy um and KV
cache uh size. So KV cache size which relates to throughput and latency um
you want to be small and you want perplexity also to be um you
know small. So they're able to you know improve uh that
um okay so so notice that I mean for example H6 64 heads you
know the cache size goes uh it gets reduced but the validation perplexity does
go up a little bit but overall the the there's kind of advantage um
in you know making that trade-off.
Okay, so there's yet another way to do things. Um, so local attention um,
which has been explored actually quite a bit since even kind of the there's
a long former there's an open AI paper and then Mistro and I think
many others use this as well. Um, it's a very I guess a natural
idea instead of if you look at a full attention diagram it's dense n
squared. Um, and that's where a lot of your complexity comes from. Um, and
basically the idea is, uh, you're going to just attend to only the past
K tokens. Um, which means that in the KV cache, as you're generating the
sequence, you don't have to remember everything as as soon as the token kind
of falls outside your window that you have of attention, you can just like
throw it away, right? So local contention is very uh you you could say
that the KV cache size remains constant as opposed to growing with the sequence
length. So this is really good right because that means for even long se
sequences you can have um quite a small cache.
Okay. Um but you know the problem is that this still you know hurts
accuracy because if you just think about it like why are we doing attention
instead of RNN's is that we needed to have long range to MAC model
run long range dependencies and this is in some sense even to call it
attention is a little bit kind of a um overselling this this is only
looking at the local context um which is not very expressive. So what you
do here is you can interle local attention with full global attention hybrid layers.
Um so for example character AI used um for every six layers they had
one global attent global layer and five um local layers. So it looks something
in addition to cross layer attention. So it looks something like uh this um
where full attention every layer um you have to store the you know KV
cache um and for um what they did is that for every six layers
you have the full attention but in between you have this local attention and
on top of that they have KV cache sharing um locally both at the
for the local attention and the global attention. So this is like all the
tricks kind of you know not all the tricks but many of the tricks
kind of combined you know together. Um so in summary these are a few
ways to reduce the KV cache size because remember inference is memory limited. Um
so you want to reduce the cache size but you don't want to hurt
accuracy too much. And there's many ways to do it. You can lower the
dimensionality of the KV cache. You can have few KV cache vectors. You can
reduce the dimensionality of a a KV vector. You can share the KV cache
across layers. Um and also you can use local attention on some of the
layers. Okay. Any questions about um the set of tricks for reducing the KV
cache? Uh yeah. Yeah. Question about the costion. So like how many like I
feel like the weights are all being shared across the like the same layers
like do you just have like one set of weights which just like KV
that's shared across the blue ones? Yeah. So the the question is are the
weights shared? So the KV cache is shared but the weights are shared. So
what happens is the weights for doing the um you know the projection need
to be shared so there's some consistency.
Yeah. Yeah, there was another question. The the context size is is too large
every you know and then it increases the KV catch as well the contact
size when you
pump the context that is given to the trans. Yeah long then it increases
the size. So we try reducing those context by summarizing the context context. Yeah.
So the question is uh if you have really long context let's say your
prompt is huge that's going to intrinsically take a lot of KV cache um
so all these tricks can try to reduce uh that um you can do
more aggressive things that like you know there's ideas like you know just tokens
or ways to summarize the prompt um which we're not going to talk about
in this class but there's ways of that address the long prompt situation as
Okay. So now I'm going to talk about even more radical ways of uh
making inference go faster by changing the transformer. So the KV cache these are
basically variants of the transformer. Um but maybe you can actually go um outside
the transformer and and do better because the transformer wasn't really designed with you
know heavy inference workloads in mind. They were just trying to try and train
a good model that um efficiently. It was mostly about training efficiency and the
auto regression as we sort of pointed out is really causing this kind of
um you know bottleneck here with the auto regression plus the kind of the
full attention. So um we're going to talk about two directions uh state space
models and diffusion models. Um this is going to be fairly quick. Um so
the idea of state space models is actually drawing ideas from you know signal
processing and control theory. Um initially the motivation was trying to model long context
uh sequences without suffering the n squ blowup. So it wasn't necessary about inference
speed but it turns out if you solve that problem you get faster inference
too. So there's a kind of early paper on S S4 U which uses
classical uh state space models which are basically these kind of linear dynamical systems
u which are you been used to kind of model along context and sort
of shoehorning them into the kind of a modern neural um setup. Um this
work is uh allows has is you know nice in that it has sort
of this RNN kind of interpretation due to the linearity structure and also has
a you know convolution um interpretation as well. So they published this uh this
uh this paper and um you know showed that it I think worked really
well on these long context you know synthetic tasks. Um but what they found
is that what I guess what was uh discovered is that they don't really
work well for language modeling. uh and that's obviously kind of a disappointment because
a lot of the value of transformers is being able to do language well.
Um so in a series of papers there was um they sort of identified
a set of kind of synthetic tasks that captured the essence of why these
models weren't working well and that's basically these associative recall tasks. So here's a
synthetic task where you're given a basically a sequence of key value pairs and
um and the goal is to predict basically look up the key and output
the value. So in some sense it's kind of a logically a trivial task
but it's long sequence because I can have a lot of key value pairs
and um I'm going to have to look far back. It can be arbitrary
long dependence and you can see that local attention is not going to work
very well because it's just going to remember the last few sequences and um
what the problem with states space models is that they're sort of good for
these kind of signal processing tasks but um really this is like you need
to go isolate a particular key value pair and pull out the the answer
and for those type of tasks it didn't really work. So there's a bunch
of work um I'm not citing there's like hyena h3 and then mamba um
which basically tweaked the or changed the hssm um to basically handle these associative
recall tasks and eventually it worked better up to kind of 1b scale was
matching you know transformers um and uh mamb idea of mamba has been popular
and scaled up um even to a 52b um um by AI21 folks. Um
notice that in this case they still had to use a transformer. So a
transformer but only every I guess eight layers they had a transformer. The rest
of them were mamba layers. Um and so that still get led to a
fairly big you know uh savings and and speed
up. Um
and uh but more recently there's this kind of revival of this older idea
called linear
attention.
Um where instead of um let's see if I can make this bigger. Um
is actually a kind of a very simple idea. So you know what local
attention or sliding window attention is? Um linear attention is this idea that uh
you
essentially in so in this basically in the um attention computation there's a key
and a query and you uh dotproduct them and you take the x of
that which is basically giving you a x kernel. So you can basically take
a tailor expansion of that and write that computation as basically dotproducts of some
nonlinear map. So then what you essentially have is you you can think about
for every uh key value position you are basically applying some sort of nonlinearity
blowing up into some space and then doing some linear computation over it. And
because it's linear attention, it actually kind of behaves like an RNN and it's
linear in the the sequence length rather than quadratic. I know that was a
little bit uh fast, but um I just want to give you sort of
the the taste of it. And so this idea has been actually uh scaled
up quite successfully. So there's this um um organization called Miniax that's training um
pretty legitimate models um up to 456 billion parameteres. Um and they use this
basically linear attention idea. Now they have to use full attention um still once
in a while. It seems it I don't think um people have been able
to get around having some full attention but at least it seems like people
have been able to get rid of most of full attention in like most
of the layers are not full attention anymore. They're just either linear layers or
local attention layers which are much much more efficient.
Okay, so the linear plus local attention um you know now are actually yielding
serious state-of-the-art models and it's probably you know safe to say that well I
don't know what's uh exactly the the closed model providers are doing but I
would suspect that there would be at least as kind of advance in terms
of as efficient as um this and leveraging sparsity
So it's it's kind of an interesting question when people ask like well you
know is trans attention all you need is transformers it well you know yes
and no I mean I guess in some sense there is still the sense
squared there maybe we'll be able to get rid of it but most of
the transformer has been like pretty radically changed by having other much lighter weight
you know components and you're still able to get much of the same and
kind of accuracy And all of this is, you know, really helpful for inference
because on these non-ful attention layers, you're basically replacing the ordered t KV cache
which grows as a sequence length with something that's uh constant. And there's there's
papers by um uh that followup I think they uh on the based paper
where did that go? there's some f uh either in this paper or in
follow-up work analyzing basically the trade-off between the KV size and the ability to
do uh various types of kind of recall tasks which makes sense because if
you don't store very much you won't be able to solve certain tasks but
there is this trade-off curve that you can try to play with okay so
that's all I'll say about um the state space models So now let's talk
about a completely different style of uh generation models, diffusion models. So diffusion models
have been very popular image generation but they turn out to be fairly tricky
to get working in text although there recently have been some advances here. So
the idea of diffusion is that you instead of generating all regressively you just
generate every token in parallel. So obviously if you only do that you know
via some simple layer it's not going to be very good. You can't generate
all the words in parallel and expect it to be coherent. But what you
do is you iterate and you keep on refining um this this generation until
it gets to your final uh generation that you output.
And the the idea behind generating in parallel, you're no longer auto reggressively, you
know, bound and that generating all tokens in parallel well can be done in
parallel. So you get to saturate your your G GPUs relatively easy as long
as your context length is large enough. Um so recently there's this uh and
session labs has um produced some pretty interesting models. Um there's not much written
about them but you can see kind of a a demo of the generation
and process. it just kind of generates um code instantaneously but it's obviously kind
of broken code and then it uh you know kind of refineses over time.
So, and this is one of their their benchmarks that show that at least
on coding, I'm not sure about other uh tasks that if you look at
that at tokens per second, these models are like way out here in terms
of speed compared to anything that's transformer. Even Jamba remember is like a hybrid
mamba um um uh transformer architecture is is quite slow compared to these diffusion
models. So now whether diffusion models are you know be will be kind of
general purpose and powerful enough in all these that remains to be seen but
I think it's you know you have such a lead on the the kind
of the token speed here that um even if you um I think you
can put more compute and kind of recover some of the accuracy uh losses
if you if you need to. Okay. So the the summary here is that
I think this whole kind of architecture novel architecture thing is actually really exciting
for inference um because um they allow you to sidestep kind of fundamental obstacles
right so if you're dealing with attention you just have this fundamental KV cache
obstacle that you can quantize you can optimize but it's still there and and
so by making a kind of safe space model you're shrinking that to like
a constant size and as long as you can keep up the accuracy which
is big if um then you win big time. Same with the diffusion models
auto reggressive generation is a key bottleneck. Now if you just generalize generate things
in parallel now all of a sudden you kind of like change the game
you know completely. So there's much more work to be done here um in
proving inference. So as you can see now is the inference game is is
much broader than it seems at first sight. It's not really about kind of
necessarily the systems optimizations to make it fast although you obviously need those but
I think the real gains are coming from um like real radical changes in
architecture. Um okay so I have about 10 minutes left. I'll go through these
quickly. Uh quantization and model pruning. So quantization the key idea is just reduce
the precision of the numbers. Okay. So easily e very easy to do and
the thought is that less memory means uh less bytes transferred higher sorry there
should be lower latency higher throughput. Um and you do have to worry about
accuracy of course that's the the trade-off. Um if you look at the different
types of uh you know formats FP32 used for training not used for inference
really um BF-16 is sort of the default for inference. You can go down
to FP8 or INT8 which now is um is less accurate but much you
know cheaper than even FP8. Um so people do do a bunch of inference
in int 8 which if you look at the range I mean it's an
integer between 127 minus 128 which is not that uh it's pretty low precision
and people even going down to in4 which is they're not oh yeah so
int4 is pretty you know low um there's also other ways you can do
okay so you can so once you kind of decide that you want to
um quantize. I guess you could do several things. You can train with a
quantization, but obviously that means you need to retrain models and more I guess
commonly you do post-training quantization where you take an existing model and you try
to quantize it and try not to screw things up too much. Um so
the there's a paper called element int 8 which I'll I'll talk through you
know kind of briefly. So in quantization um basically what happens is that you
take your you know your your vector which is let's say FP16 um and
then you need to figure out the dynamic range right if you want to
pack it into int 8 you need to figure out what the largest value
is and once you figure that out you can kind of um you know
divide uh by that and multiply by 128 and then you get your integers
and then if you need to um dequantize then you kind of go the
other way. So, so basically quantization means that remember memory is a bandwidth, right?
So, bottleneck. So, you're all your transfers are happening in um in in end
date but when you actually do the you know I guess uh you sometimes
have to upcast to um a floating point to actually do the arithmetic. Um
okay so the problem with int8 is that not everything you know fits nicely
and you have these outliers which appear in larger networks that screw things up.
So what this paper did is that you take a this matrix you identify
the really large outlier values and then you handle them separately use in full
16bit precision and then do the most the vast majority
in 88. Um so this works well but is actually a bit um you
know uh slower. So the motivation here wasn't inference speed but more even being
able to fit your model into u memory. There's another paper called activation aware
quantization and here uh the idea is that you you're kind of quantizing the
bas kind of the the weights but you're going to figure out which weights
to quantize based on the the activations um you know really quickly this you're
going down to actually in three um and this obviously reduces memory by quite
a bit and leads to a 3x uh you know speed up And so
the general idea here is that you want to um you get a trained
model and it just happens that some of the weights or activations are going
to be abnormally large. So for those you handle separately and then everything else
you can kind of work in low you know precision. Okay. Um talk about
model pruning um ideas very like quantization. It's sort of the basic idea is
very simple. you just rip out parts of an expensive model to make it
cheaper and then you fix it up. So in this Nvidia paper what they
do is they first identify important either layers or heads or hidden dimensions um
using a small calibration size. say use some you know uh simple scores to
compute that and then you just remove the unimportant layers or hidden units or
heads and then now if you just take that model it's going to be
clearly worse right but so then the last step is you distill the original
model into the prune model so you kind of repair the model from the
initialization which is your prune so you're not starting from scratch you're starting from
something that's worse but hopefully not worse and hopefully retains a lot of the
same structural properties of the original model. It's just maybe not kind of like
calibrated in some sense. Um, and the results are pretty good on that. So
they have these 15 billion parameter models that they're able to reduce to 8B
with hardly any drop in this I guess at least according to MMLU and
then down to 4B with uh some drop but you also are going down
quite a bit to a 4B model. Okay. So um so maybe summarize this
taking shortcuts idea. You can uh reduce inference complexity without hurting accuracy. You can
do it from scratch where you just define a fresh architecture that's by construction
fast and just train it. Or you can distill you define that architecture. You
can take a slow model and you figure out a some sort of scheme
to initialize the new model with the old model. And then you basically do
distillation. Um so okay so now all of these are a little bit unsatisfying
because they're lossy. So you get massive speed ups but you always wonder well
maybe this model isn't as actually good as original. So speculative decoding or speculative
sampling allows you to um basically have your cake and eat it too. So
recall there's two stages of inference. You prefill um which you're given a sequence,
you encode all the tokens in parallel. This is compute limited um which is
great. Notice that this also gives you log probabilities for each of the tokens.
And then there's generation which is one token at a time. It's memory limit.
It's slow. So in other words, checking is faster than generation. So intuitively this
makes sense. But hopefully now you also appreciate the math behind why this is
true. Um and the speculative sampling idea is actually really really again it was
proposed in parallel by these two independent teams from Google. Um and uh the
idea
is to use a cheap draft model P to just run ahead and generate
some tokens and then you're going to evaluate those tokens with a target model
and because evaluation of given tokens is just prefilled so you can do that
in parallel which is fast and then you accept it if it looks good.
So uh this is what it looks like in uh real life. So if
you're using a big model generating one token at a time that's slow but
in speculative decoding you have the draft model that's racing ahead generating um a
lot of tokens and using the big model to essentially verify and sometimes it
will reject and sometimes it'll accept and the acceptance rate basically determines how fast
of a speed up you you have. Okay. So here is the more formal
um algorithm. Um so you're going to have a look ahead of K. So
you're going to use your draft model and generate K tokens auto reggressively. So
this is hopefully fast because your draft model is small and then you're given
these K tokens that you generated and I'm going to score them based on
I'm going to compute the probability under the target model Q. Now I'm going
to decide whether I want to accept this not or not. So I go
through each token and I'm going to essentially accept it with probability um Q
over P and the one just is uh make sure this you know probabilities
are between zero and one. Um if this kind of looks like if people
are familiar with Metropolis Hastings this is kind of where this uh this kind
of comes from. Um so intuitively you're you're sampling with P. Um so you
need to divide that out because you don't want P you want Q. So
this is kind of importance weight um on this. So if you accept it
then great you kind of move on and you look at the next draft
token and so on. Um and if you don't accept it then you're going
to sample from the the the target model the slow model but you kind
of do this correction where you've already tried to sample using P. So you
don't need to do that anymore. You subtract it out and you sample from
Q. So this is basically kind of a rejection sampling with a proposal P
and a target uh sorry target Q. Um the only difference is that um
you are sampling you you injection sampling you if you reject then you reject
and you just try again and you try again. Um, and here we don't
want to keep on kind of looping forever. Uh because if you reject, we're
just going to say, "Okay, fine. We'll bite the bullet and just sample from
the the more expensive model." So the cool thing here is that you're guaranteed
to get an exact sample from the target model. Okay, so those of you
familiar with sampling, this is it shouldn't be too surprising. You're able to use
kind of prior information to speed up sampling. Um but in a language modeling
context this is kind of nice. Um I'm going to skip the uh this
is not really a proof. This is just kind of some derivation to show
that for a case of vocab 2 it why this these formulas kind of
give you the right unbiased sampling procedure. Um and it works uh pretty well.
So the accuracy uh is you know it should be actually the the same
since it's the same model. But maybe there's some randomness there. But the speed
up is you're getting a factor of two speed up
essentially. Um
so and so in practice what you do is you take you have something
like a 70B model and your draft model is much much smaller. Um and
if your target model is 80B 8B then your draft model might be 1B.
And you generally want to make the draft model as closest to your target
as possible. Um and so if you're doing some distillation that could um make
it even better. There's a bunch of this is a pretty uh hot area
of of research and inference. There's a lot of ways to improve this process.
Um you can use um Medusa which is this uh way to have the
draft model instead of generating auto reggressively sample multiple tokens in parallel or eagle
where you're actually taking highle features of the target model and pumping them into
the draft to generate. So the draft model doesn't actually have to stand alone.
It can be kind of glom on to the target model to help it
generate. Um so uh summary exact sampling from the target model thanks to math.
Um and this exploits the symmetry between checking and generation right so or um
prefill and there's actually a lot of room for innovation on a draft model
um which can you know everything that we talked about before where you can
have different radical architectures different ways of quantizing all of those apply right the
only thing is that um you get to basically guarantee that you're getting exact
act uh sample. Okay. So now I'll go uh I'm out of time but
quickly go through the um the question that came up earlier which is that
in practice when you're serving there's live traffic requests come at different times. Um
they finish at they have some of them have shared prefixes some of them
don't. They have different lengths. So it's very
heterogeneous um in comparison to training where you get basically a dense block of
tokens and you're basically going to p push it through your GPU at at
full speed. So what do you do in this case? So there's a series
of papers that kind of ex explore this um and the the basic idea
is is this is so the last two parties are more of a kind
of systems level um contribution. So the idea is that you don't wait for
batches to, you know, the the train leaves. There's no the train doesn't um
wait for you. Um so when a new batch comes, you're just going to
put it in, right? Which means that um the the sort of this uh
the the the um worker that's generating tokens needs to kind of hand control
back to theuler every step. So you generate a token, come back to the
scheduleuler and say if there's new um uh new u requests then they get
stuck in and then it kind of continues. So you're kind of not wasting
any time waiting around for requests. Um now there's a kind of a problem
with batching I think which is behind the question. Um batching works when everything's
the same dimensionality but every request might be a different length. So there's this
idea of selective batching where um you basically break up your computation for attention.
Everything has to be handled separately. But for your MPs remember which are the
bulk of the computation you can actually take tensors of different sizes and you
just flatten them. And because they don't interact um they can just like be
kind of kind of along for the ride in the batch dimension. Okay, I
know that was fast, but uh I'll just quickly go over page detention. Now,
um this is the the paper behind VLM, which some of you probably have
used. Um and this addresses the memory usage problem. So, if you have a
KV cache and prompts are coming in and finishing, then your cache is going
to get fragmented. So, you're going to have um you're going to allocate a
bunch of uh space for a request, but you don't know how many tokens
are getting generated. So um there's going to be internal fragmentation and then there's
also going to be external fragmentation where there's padding between the the requests and
responses. So that's no good. So the page attention basically says remember operating systems
we have um and how kind of virtual memory works we divide the KV
cache into a sequence of contiguous blocks and then we just put them wherever
um we find white space. So if you have two requests coming in then
um they might just you know the first request might be here here and
here and the second request might be here and here. So the blocks are
the things that you're going to keep contiguous and that's going to give you
your allow you time to coales your memory.
Um so you can also play these tricks where if you have uh sharing
of prefixes then there's another idea from uh operating systems which is copy on
write. So you basically maintain reference counters for how many basically uh sequences are
using this particular block and then if you need to kind of diverge and
have blocks go in different directions then you copy and you reduce the reference
count. Um there's a bunch of other VLM optimizations which I won't go through
but basically the summary is remember your your operating systems classes you can apply
them to inference as well. Okay, so quick summary, inference is really really important.
It's where um and the characteristics are distinct from training. You're memory limited and
it's also dynamic. So which leads a bunch of uh uh new challenges. We
saw a whole host of different techniques around new architectures, quantization, pruning, distillation, um
speculative decoding. uh there's ideas from systems which can allow you to better use
your memory um overlap communication and compute and things like that but but I
would say that there's probably even more um opportunity in sort of the modeling
and architecture because if you think about it all you you don't inference narrowly
is inference in a particular model how do I run this but who cares
running about that particular model you care delivering good accuracy given your resource budget.
So a lot of these ideas that are trying to change the reduce the
KV cache, changing the transformer are basically ways to sidestep the problem and say,
well, I have something that's more efficient and if I can train in a
way that gets me better accuracy, then then I win. Okay, so that's all
I have and I will see you next time. Then we're back to scaling
lots.